Guide to the Pitchforks of Duke University records, 1980 - 2008 UA.31.07.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pitchforks of Duke University records
1980 - 2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pitchforks of Duke University
Ward, Benjamin Frank, Jr., 1948-2013
UA.31.07.0003
6.5 Linear Feet
Contains the records of the Pitchforks of Duke University, a men's a cappella singing group. Types of materials include articles of incorporation, a constitution, certificates, correspondence, applications, press, flyers, clippings, photographs, rosters, and sound recordings. Major subjects include student life at Duke University, male college students, vocal performance groups, and student groups. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Some materials in off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Sound recordings in this collection may require reformatting before use. Please contact University Archives staff before visiting to use this portion of the collection.
Provenance
The Pitchforks of Duke University records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1985; 2003; 2008; and 2019.
Historical Note
The Pitchforks, a mostly undergraduate men's a cappella singing group, began singing together in 1979, in response to the need for men's informal singing at Duke University. The group was chartered as a student organization in 1981. The founding officers of the Pitchforks were: Robert S. Clarke, Frank E. Block, James Bulleit, Eliot McCrory, and Kurt T. Uphoff.
The group's a cappella repertoire includes a variety of popular and classic songs in various musical styles including ballads, jazz, blues, spirituals, folk, and traditional barbershop songs. The Pitchforks perform at hospitals, nursing homes, hotels, private clubs, weddings, and on other college campuses. Their on-campus events include small performances for sororities, Homecoming, the Blackwell Arch show, the Dance Marathon, the annual Jamboree, and the Gothic Christmas Concert. The Pitchforks also host other high school and college a cappella singing groups.
The Pitchforks have recorded several albums and are currently active at Duke University. Other Duke University a cappella groups are: Something Borrowed, Something Blue, Lady Blue, Out of the Blue, Rhythm and Blue, Deja Blue, and Speak of the Devil.
Collection Overview
Contains articles of incorporation, a constitution, certificates, correspondence, applications, press, flyers, clippings, photographs, rosters, and sound recordings of the Pitchforks, a Duke University men's singing group. Records date from 1980-2008 (bulk 1980-1985).
Choral singing; Photographs; Sound recordings; Clippings (information artifacts); Male college students -- United States -- North Carolina -- Durham; Choral societies -- United States; Choruses, Secular (Men's voices), Unaccompanied; Popular music -- 1981-1990; Students' songs -- North Carolina; Popular songs; Duke University -- Songs and music; Duke University -- Students; Pitchforks of Duke University
- Subject Files, 1980-1989
  - Articles of incorporation and constitution, ca. 1980- 1986 (Box 1)
  - ASDU charters, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Statement of Commitment (of members to the Pitchforks group), 1986 (Box 1)
  - Membership certificates, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Audition materials, general, ca. 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Audition callbacks, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Audition applications, ca. 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Jamboree, general materials and press, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Concerts and events, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - The Pitchforks album materials, 1983 (Box 1)
  - It's not Rock 'n' Roll but I like it! Album materials, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Flyers, advertisements, and general publicity, ca. 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Song lists for performances, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Logo materials, ca. 1980 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (negatives), 1983 (Box 1)
  - Rosters, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, ca. 1980-1983 (Box 1)
- Sound recordings, 1983-2008
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Sound recordings may require reformatting before use. Please contact University Archives staff before visiting to use this portion of the collection.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Please contact University Archives staff to access related Pitchforks master recordings.
  - Pitchforks of Duke University, 1983, 12" disc, Commercial LP (Box 1)
  - It's Not Rock 'n' Roll but I like it! The 1983-1984 Pitchforks of Duke University, 1984, 12" disc, Commercial LP (Box 1)
  - Pitchforks of Duke University: Tonal Eclipse, 1992, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - Pitchforks of Duke University: Underground, 1994, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - Ninth St.: The Pitchforks of Duke University, 1996, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - Bad for the piano: The Pitchforks, 2002, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - A Gothic Christmas: The Pitchforks of Duke University, 2003, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - The Pitchforks of Duke University: Bring it Back, 2006, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - The Pitchforks: Disconcert, 2008, CD, Reference Copy (Box 1)
  - Benjamin F. Ward, Jr., 1981 Oct 10 (Box 4)
    Includes recordings of pianist Benjamin F. Ward, Jr. performing a recital for Arts in Duke Chapel. Selections include works by Johann Sebastian Bach; Cesar Franck; Claude Debussy; and Frederic Chopin. As an Adjunct Associate Professor in the Duke University Department of Philosophy, and the Associate Dean for Faculty Program, Ward directed and performed with The Pitchforks.
  - Benjamin F. Ward, Jr., 1983 Sep 25; 1 Reels (Box 4)
    Content includes pianist Benjamin Ward performing works of Federic Chopin.
  - Master recordings, 1984-1998; 6 boxes
    Contents include masters for The Pitchforks' recordings.
    - Master recordings, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
    - Master recordings, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Master recordings, 1981-1987, 1994-1998 (Box 4)
    - Master recordings, 1994 Apr 3 (Box 5)
    - Master recordings, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Master recordings, 1984 (Box 7)